<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The hearse of the renowned, the Right Honourable Robert Earle of Essex and Ewe, Viscount Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier and Lovaine, sometime Captaine Lord Generall of the armies raised for the defence of King and Parliament As it was represented in a sermon, preached in the Abbey Church at Westminster, at the magnificent solemnity of his funerall, Octob. 22. 1646. By Richard Vines. Published by order of the House of Peeres.</title>
            <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 64 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825297</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29677</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29677)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2140:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The hearse of the renowned, the Right Honourable Robert Earle of Essex and Ewe, Viscount Hereford, Lord Ferrers of Chartley, Bourchier and Lovaine, sometime Captaine Lord Generall of the armies raised for the defence of King and Parliament As it was represented in a sermon, preached in the Abbey Church at Westminster, at the magnificent solemnity of his funerall, Octob. 22. 1646. By Richard Vines. Published by order of the House of Peeres.</title>
                  <author>Vines, Richard, 1600?-1656.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p. : port. (metal cut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T.R. and E.M. for Abel Roper at the sign of the Sun against Dunstans Church in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A sermon preached at the funerall of the Right Honourable Robert Earle of Essex, &amp;c.</note>
                  <note>With an errata slip.</note>
                  <note>Probably the second edition (Wing V554 and V554A, variants of each other, constitute the probable first). Quire A is in the same setting in all, with the imprint altered.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Essex, Robert Devereux, --  Earl of, 1591-1646.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:29677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Robert Earl of Essex</figDesc>
                  <head>Robert Earle of Essex, his Excellence, Generall of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Army. Imployed for the defence of the Protestant Religion, the ſafety of his Ma<hi rend="sup">ties</hi> Person, and of the Parliament: the preſeruation of the Lives &amp; Liberties of the Subiects. Aetatis ſuae. 56. </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29677:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HEARSE OF THE Renowned, THE RIGHT HONOURABLE ROBERT EARLE OF <hi>ESSEX</hi> and <hi>Ewe,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Hereford,</hi> Lord <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> of <hi>Chartley, Bourchier.</hi> and <hi>Lovaine,</hi> ſometime Captaine Lord Generall of the Armies raiſed for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>As it was repreſented in a <hi>Sermon,</hi> preached in the Abbey Church at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at the Magnificent Solemnity of his Funerall, <hi>Octob.</hi> 22. 1646.</p>
            <p>By RICHARD VINES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Eccleſ. 12. 5.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Man goeth to his long home, and the mourners goe about the ſtreets.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of Peeres.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>Abel Roper</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Sun</hi> againſt <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in Fleet-ſtreet. 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29677:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29677:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE The Houſe of PEERES Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have performed what ſervice I am able to the memory of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Lord, deceaſed, And to the Commands of that Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and Noble <hi>Triumvirate</hi> which gave being to this Sermon. And to your Lordſhips by whoſe Order I have adventured upon this
<pb facs="tcp:29677:3"/> Publication: All men (except ſuch whoſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moroſity or malignity doth account, <hi>vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra in laude, praeſentià in faſtidio)</hi> muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the worth, the valour, the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe which lie under the Robes you weare, and that it is not a meere borrowed Opinion which makes you Honorable, but the refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction or rebounding back of that upon you, which went firſt out from you: But this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon will teach you, that Titles of Honour are written in duſt, and that Princes and great men muſt fall, their very Monuments are mortall, and will in time be found as <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chemedes</hi> his Tomb (by <hi>Cicero) in vepretis,</hi> over-growne with Thorns and Bryers; and that light of memory which ſhines after your Sun-ſet, is but like the Moon which wanes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by degrees: No glory that's woven in the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Tapeſtry of this world but will loſe colour, decay, and periſh, but ſaving grace and the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a
<pb facs="tcp:29677:3"/> poſſeſſion for eternity, your zealous agency for the Church and State will carry you as far to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Immortality as any other Chariot in this world. Its as much as nothing when one can ſay no more of a man then is ſaid of ſome great ones, that they <hi>reigned</hi> and <hi>died.</hi> The <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 36. 33.</note> Lord give you hearts actuated with zeal for God, together with a right temperament of counſels, knowing that you are over a people who (as <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaith) <hi>nec tota<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſervitutem pati poſſunt nec totam libertatem,</hi> and if your fall do come before you ſee, or reap the fruit of your labours: The Lord make you ſuch as may take comfort with you, and leave Honour behinde you, ſo prayeth</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt humble and unworthy ſervant, in and for Jeſus Chriſt, RICHARD VINES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:29677:4"/>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Die Veneris</hi> 23. <hi>Octob.</hi> 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by the Lords in Parliament aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, That this Houſe gives thanks to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Vines</hi> for the great pains by him taken yeſterday in the Sermon hee preached at the ſolemnization of the Funerall of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> deceaſed: And hee is hereby deſired to Print and Publiſh the ſame, which is not to be Printed by any but by Authority under his own hand.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Jo. Browne Cleric. Parliamentorum.</signed> I appoint <hi>Abel Roper</hi> to print this Sermon. <signed>Richard Vines.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29677:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED At the Solemnization of the Funerall of the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ROBERT Earle of <hi>ESSEX,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S that Lot ſent forth to attach a particular man, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7. 16. did move <hi>gradatim,</hi> and by ſteps, taking firſt the Tribe, then the Family, then the Houſe, and at laſt the Man; after which manner of progreſſion, though at fewer ſteps, <hi>Jonathan</hi> was alſo taken, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 14. 42. So doe the trackes or <hi>veſtigia</hi> appearing to your eye, lead you at two or three removes to the moſt ſad occaſion of this extraordinary and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent ſolemnity. The Eſcocheons which are the <hi>Index of the Family</hi> do ſpeak firſt, and tell the name of that honourable Family which this <hi>Lot hath taken.</hi> And this ſable field of men, charged with a ſtately Herſe, honoured with ſo great a confluence of names and titles of honour granted either by the Sword or Gowne, whether Honourable, Worſhipfull, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:29677:5"/> and that in this place, where the <hi>Dij majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum gentium</hi> have their Shrines, where the <hi>Lions of England</hi> have uſually put off their <hi>exuvias,</hi> and where Majeſtie and highneſſe have laid up what of Mortality they had, doth proclaime him to bee ſome Prince, or great name of that Family, <hi>whom the Lot hath taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then the Military Equipage, the mourning Drumme, the broken Launce, the <hi>inſignia</hi> &amp; Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Warre reverſed, and in a mournful poſture; The Truncheon in a dead hand, doe ſpeake the very man. It is <hi>Jonathan that is taken.</hi> And ſhall <hi>Jonathan</hi> dye that hath wrought ſo great ſalvation in <hi>Iſrael?</hi> It is (alas) too late to ſay, ſhall <hi>Jonathan</hi> dye, This <hi>Jonathan</hi> cannot be reſcued by the love of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> therefore I muſt ſadly lay the Scene in one that is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready <note place="margin">1 Sam. 14. 45.</note> fallen: for do not yee know that there is a Prince and a great man <hi>fallen</hi> this day in Iſrael?</p>
            <div type="sermon_proper">
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>2 SAM. 3. 38.</bibl>
                  <q>Know yee not that there is a Prince, and a great man fallen this day in Iſrael?</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Text preſents you with the Herſe of <hi>Abner;</hi> a Prince and a great man fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> This day preſents you with a paralell Herſe of a Prince, and a great man fallen in <hi>England;</hi> both of them magnificently attended with the drooping ſtatelines
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:29677:5"/> of publike and univerſall lamentation.</p>
               <p>That I may ſet up ſome lights about the Herſe of <hi>Abner,</hi> you may pleaſe to call to minde:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. His Office.</item>
                  <item>2. His Project.</item>
                  <item>3. His Fall.</item>
                  <item>4. His Funerall.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">1. His Office was Captaine of the Hoſt, or <hi>ſtylo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo,</hi> Lord Generall of the Forces of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> it was not ſo much becauſe he toucht King <hi>Saul</hi> in bloud, being Couſin-Germane, as in reſpect of this high com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that he is called, <hi>A Prince, and a great man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. His Project which he had upon the Anvile now at his death, was the reducement of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> unto the Scepter of <hi>David;</hi> herein his Project concurr'd with Gods; but took riſe in him, from an ill or ſuſpicious ground. <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> doth but queſtion him for familiar uſage of a Concubine of <hi>Sauls</hi> (which if true, was in thoſe times accounted a kinde of <hi>Crimen Majeſtatis)</hi> and this heats his bloud, <hi>for great Inſtruments will not beare a checke)</hi> and thereupon his Stomack brings him off to <hi>David. God uſeth the ſins and great Spirits, or animoſities, of great men (though they be not carried by Conſcience) to bring to birth his owne purpoſes and promiſes made to his</hi> Davids.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His Fall; which was by the hand of pretended revenge, but reall emulation; the ſpirit of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey</hi> was in <hi>Joab,</hi> before it was in them: He could not abide a corrivall or equall. Let great Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders looke to this; Ambition is a Planet that muſt have a whole Orbe to it ſelfe, and is impatient of Conſort.</p>
               <p n="4">4. His Funerall; and that was ſolemne and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urable
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29677:6"/> in <hi>Hebron;</hi> now the royall City, and former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Sepulchrall of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, &amp;c.</hi> At which, <hi>David</hi> was <hi>chiefe mourner,</hi> for he followed the Bed or Herſe, <hi>verſe</hi> 31. and he was <hi>the Oratour</hi> that made the ſpeech of Lamentation; as he had before done for <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1. 19.</p>
               <p>Now for the Herſebefore you, let us ſee how farre it paralells with this in the Text.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Prince or great man fallen this day in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was Captaine Lord <hi>Generall</hi> of the Hoſt of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> There is agreement in the Office and Title; the Text could not be proper to any fallen under our Meridian unto this day: but unto this new ſtarre created by the Parliament, and ariſing in this Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon, about <hi>July</hi> 1642. and now eclipſed or fallen.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His project is written in a copy fairer then the originall, and goes farre beyond that of <hi>Abner.</hi> The reducement of divided <hi>Iſrael</hi> into one hive is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what alike in both. But here is no effeminate ſpark that raiſeth the ſpirit of this great man into a flame; no ſuch cauſe of his engagement, but the defence of thoſe pupill twinnes, the two bleeding ſiſters ready to dye in each the others boſome, the <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty</hi> of the Subjects of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. His fall is cleere of the diſaſter in <hi>Abners</hi> ſtory; he falls not by the hand of ſome unworthy and villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous deſert or of him, made bold by his vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or flight, as <hi>Pompey</hi> did; nor by the juſt fury of an oppreſſed Senate as <hi>Caeſar</hi> did; nor by the arts and ſtratagems of a treacherous death as <hi>Abner</hi> did; <hi>The hand of</hi> Joab <hi>is not in all this;</hi> but by an <hi>Euthanaſy</hi> (which <hi>Auguſtus</hi> wiſht for) a faire death. Hee dyed in peace.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29677:6"/> 4. His Funerall for the ſtate of it certainly over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matches the patterne. Here are the two Houſes of Parliament, the map of all England in two globes, powring out their ſorrowes, and paying their kiſſes of Honourable farewell to his tutelar ſword.</p>
               <p>The Princes of the Land that quarter with him in in honour and in bloud, doe quarter with his herſe this day in blacke and mourning.</p>
               <p>The flowre of the renowned City of <hi>London</hi> (far ſurpaſſing the meanneſs of <hi>Abners Hebron)</hi> doe traile their teares after his Herſe, and are come to put upon him their <hi>civicam coronam,</hi> their civicall crown of Honour, <hi>propter ſervatos cives</hi> for their ſaved Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</p>
               <p>The reverend Judges and the Worthies of that gowne, doe preſent the mourning teares of the lawes that pay this tribute for their freedome from all An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinomian prerogative.</p>
               <p>The honourable ſouldiery, thoſe great names which while they wore his Orenge in the field, could have daunted death it ſelfe, doe now in change of colour weepe over him (and what marble weepes not in ſuch change of weather?) <hi>David</hi> that could take a lion by the beard, yet weepes at the Herſe of <hi>Abner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The gowne alſo hath its ranke with the ſword in this great Army of mourners. The Aſſembly of Divines whoſe prayers hee ſomtimes valued and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted, neede not be diſtreined for their contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of teares &amp; grief, they muſt wrap up in a cloth, and lay up behind the Ephod this Goliah'-conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſword in memory of a very cordiall and noble Patron.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:29677:7"/>
               <p> Laſtly, what ſhould I ſay of thoſe ſtarres that come not into any conſtellation. I meane perſons of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not within the rankes, yet within the line of this Lamentation, together with that infinite multitude of all ſorts, from Cedars to the hyſop, that doe not onely come to fill their eyes, but to empty them? I muſt conclude, to ſay as the cryer of the <hi>Ludi ſaecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lares</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> (which were but once in a hundred yeares.) <hi>Come and ſee that which ye never ſaw before,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Plin. l.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 28.</note> 
                  <hi>nor ſhall ever ſee againe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If yet it be replyed that <hi>Abners</hi> Funerall hath one point or two of State above us, <hi>David a mourner,</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>an oratour.</hi> I ſay but this; The teares of <hi>David</hi> were at this time in great part Compurgators of that ſuſpicion which he might lye under; of having a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in that wherein <hi>Joab</hi> had his hand, which kinde of teares we have not, nor could wiſh to have, though <hi>Davids;</hi> only in the orator, <hi>David,</hi> that made the ſpeech wee are exceeded; and I am glad that ſuch a State as this is inferiour and deficient in nothing, but that wherein my poore ſervice lies.</p>
               <p>By this unparallelling parallell, you may eaſily ſee that my diſcourſe will be divided between two <hi>noble Generalls:</hi> and firſt let us come to the Text, wherein <hi>David</hi> ſpeakes ſomething <hi>of</hi> the dead, and ſomething <hi>to</hi> the living.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the dead.</hi> That a Prince and great man is fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len this day in Iſrael.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the living. Know yee not.</hi> It concernes you to <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vatablus</hi> in Annot.</note> know, or I would have you take notice both of it, &amp; that I am weake this day, though annointed King, and that the ſonnes of <hi>Zeruiah</hi> are too hard for me, ſo that I cannot execute juſtice at preſent upon the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:29677:7"/> bloody hand that hath given us this ſtroke.</p>
               <p>Concerning that which is ſpoken of the dead, therein you ſhall finde the reaſon or ſpring of the teares of this lamentation. <hi>A Prince and a great man fallen, and fallen, this day in Iſrael.</hi> This day <hi>in-Iſrael</hi> hath the Emphaſis in it. In this nick of time wherein <hi>Iſrael</hi> was upon the point of reducement by the agency and uſefull contributions of this great man, who ſeemed to be the onely Pilot that could have put the ſhip into quiet harbour, or at leaſt a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great ſteerſ-man in the worke. This day is hee fallen, and ſo <hi>Iſrael,</hi> if not more alienated by his fall, yet remaineth in diſtraction and unſettlement: and <hi>this day</hi> wherein I cannot give them juſt reparation, if they ſhould demand it of mee; if any ſhall deny that there is any accent or emphaſis in the word <hi>this day in</hi> Iſrael, doe but borrow the reflexion of light from the ſtory, and that will cleare it.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not crumble that I have to ſay into literall and ſyllabicall minuts, leaſt I be of their number: <hi>qui</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gallius.</hi> Doct.</note> 
                  <hi>verborum minutijs rerum frangunt pondera,</hi> but will draw up the matter into this theam or head;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fall of a Prince and a great man in the time of his agency and uſefulneſſe for the ſettlement of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions of Iſrael, is juſt reaſon of a ſad and ſolemne lamentation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This point I will open by parts, and thoſe words. <hi>Know yee not,</hi> ſhall bring up the uſes of it, in the rear.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The ſubject of this lamentation is <hi>a Prince and a great man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prince</hi> to our Engliſh eares, ſounds the firſt maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line branch or ſurcle ſhooting from the ſtem of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie. But the Scripture which ſpeakes no Treaſon,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29677:8"/> gives this title to Captains in War, and generally to men <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in headſhip or power, whether Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Judg. 4. 2. 2 King. 9. 5.</note> or Senatorian; yea, though a man bee but the fore-man of his ranke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Great man</hi> is a note of ſome ſingular eminencie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ordinary trees of the wood, and is a title gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven even to a <hi>Nabal</hi> that hath 3000. ſheep and 1000. <note place="margin">1 Sam. 25. 2.</note> goats, which is the meaneſt ranke of greatneſſe.</p>
               <p>But where a <hi>great man</hi> is added to a <hi>Prince,</hi> it may well import as much as <hi>magnificent,</hi> a man of power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful intereſt, great valour, honourable atchievements, noble activity in his place. <hi>Magnus</hi> is an addition or hatchment by which <hi>Alexander, Pompey, Carolus,</hi> &amp;c. have beene ſirnamed, for their great ſervices or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits. So that a man by his orb or place he is ſet in, is <hi>Princeps:</hi> but by his influence and beams of worth, raying from him upon the ſublunary Commons, he is <hi>Magnus.</hi> It is an excellent conjunction, a <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>great man.</hi> According to ſtyle of honour with us, a man may be noble by birth, diſcent, or blood. And though I be none of the new <hi>Switzers,</hi> that could wiſh Princes Canton'd into the common level; yet I may put you in mind that <hi>Antiquity of Race</hi> is but a Moſs of time growing upon the back of worth or vertue: And if a man carry not the primigeniall vertue with him, which firſt made his race noble, he is but a flower by change of ſoile degenerated into a weed, as having nothing in him but the wax or mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, without the form and ſtamp of Nobleneſſe. And you know alſo that Nobility is often times the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Prince his fancy; which when there is no intrinſecall worth to be the ſupporter of it, is (as <hi>Charren</hi> ſaith) but Nobility by parchment. It's a <note place="margin">Cap. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Nobilitate.</note>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29677:8"/> brave conſociation, when the goodneſſe and activity that makes you great, is as high as the place which makes you Princes: for if that crazy fancy take a man which poſſeſt ſome great ones; they would be called Gods, and perſonate an oſtentation of greatneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove men; it may bewray pride &amp; madneſſe; but can never ſo far deceive the ſenſe of underlings, but that they will ſay as the Cobler did to <hi>Caligula,</hi> in that ſtate and humour, that hee was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> a great <hi>Dotard.</hi> It is the acting of your power and place, which makes you great. I cannot teach you to be princes, <hi>Fortuitum eſt;</hi> but I can tell you how to be great men: not great in the glaſſe which Paraſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call flattery holds before you, but indeed; and that is thus: Fill the ſphere of your activity, the Church and State, the Towne or Countrey, with the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and benigne influences that flow from intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call worth: make the times the better for you: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine by your example your inferiours to know God, and reform their Families. Let not Profaneſſe hide it ſelfe under the wing of your patronage, nor leſſen it ſelf by the greatneſſe of your examples. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial &amp; ſpeedy Juſtice, with ſweet refreſhing Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, will make you great men in the Commonwealth; Zeal and Syncerity for God and his Houſe, will make you great men in the Church. He that will be a great man, muſt draw his lines to the center of publike good: private ends never make a great man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſubject of this Lamentation is, <hi>one Prince, one great man.</hi> Yee are called (as ſome interpret the word,) <hi>the Corners of the people; the Shields, the Gods, the Saviours, the Shepheards of the people, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God for Good, Benefactors, &amp;c.</hi> Now the fall of one great Tree makes a great gappe in the hedge;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29677:9"/> the Eclipſe of one of the greater ruling Luminaries benights the world. Our Lives, Liberties, &amp;c. are all bound up in you: we poor men ſteal into our Graves, with no greater noyſe than can be made by a branch of Roſemary, or a blacke Riband: No body takes notice of the Gloeworme, that goes out in the hedge bottome: No Comet or Prodigie, or Earth-quake tolls us the knell of our departure; but one of you is carried forth by the teares of all ISRAEL, provided that you be what your Names import, publick men, common Sanctuaries of the oppreſſed, Cities of Refuge, Altars of protection; for otherwiſe you may be ſuch as that your death would be more worth then your lives, and then, though you may be able to put men into black, you cannot put them into mourning: your death cannot be worth a teare, when your lives are not worth a prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The ſubject of this Lamentation is, a Prince &amp; <hi>A great man fallen.</hi> Death is a fall from every thing but grace: ſome do fall from a higher Scaffold; great men fall divers ſtories, from Honour, Riches, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; others from the ſurface of a level ground, having nothing to fall from but naked life. Saints dye, the gods doe fall: I need not ſtand to prove it, there is not one of you great men, but ſhall be the proofe of this point ſhortly. The Law of Death runs thus: All Honours, Titles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the contrary, in any wiſe notwithſtanding: &amp; there is no Prerogative to check this Law. I will not garniſh this Deaths-head with fine fragments of Poetry, and ſuch ſtuffe: nor would I at all ſet it before you as a ſtanding diſh, were I not ſurrounded with ſo great a Corone of Princes and great men: and haply ſome of you may be of <hi>Lewis</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29677:9"/> 
                  <hi>the Eleventh</hi> his minde, that charged all about him that they ſhould not name the terrible word <hi>Death;</hi> which yet you muſt heare of; for it is the way of all the earth; the houſe of all the living; your <hi>long home, or houſe of perpetuity:</hi> of which its ſaid, <hi>Job</hi> 3. 14. <note place="margin">1 King. 2. 2. Job 30. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Lucian<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>necy.</hi>
                  </note> Kings, Counſellours, Princes, ſmall and great, are there; and there <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: their bones and ſkeletons have no Inſcription or Titles of Honour remaining on them.</p>
               <p>The way to this houſe of all the living, is (as one ſaith) <hi>ſanguinea,</hi> or <hi>lactea;</hi> the <hi>bloudy</hi> or the <hi>milkie;</hi> that is, the common, naturall, or uſuall way.</p>
               <p>The former is troden by great men: the Prince in my Text was ſent home this way; and ſo was the firſt man in the world that dyed. The Sword hangs in a hair over the heads of great ones, who are often cut <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth <hi>Acts and Monum.</hi>
                  </note> off by the hand of emulation and animoſity. That ſlaughter-houſe of <hi>Rome</hi> (where it hath been practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Popes themſelves, who (as one of them ſaid) do rather ſucceed <hi>Romulus,</hi> making his way by blood, then <hi>Peter)</hi> hath ſent out cruell Emiſſaries to cut off famous men by a meritorious knife. How hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily may you the Worthies of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> call to mind the goodneſs of that great God, who hath bound the hands of ſuch aſſaſſinating blood-ſuckers from exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting their fury upon you, all this while, that you by renowned induſtry and zeale, have given provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Common way is troden by you great ones too: for ye Gods do die, and ye Princes ſhall fall <hi>like other men.</hi> If you run your Genealogies high enough, you will finde your ſelves but as other men, in the <hi>fretum</hi> or <hi>narrow ſea</hi> of Mankinde that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29677:10"/> divided the two Ocean worlds, <hi>the Arke of Noah:</hi> and thence if ye hold your way upward, you will be found the ſons of <hi>Adamah,</hi> common duſt: And you that are the higheſt duſt, raiſed up a puff of winde of Honour above other men, are laid, like the ſmall duſt, with one drop of rain. There is a great <hi>Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of all things, that can thunder the proud Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour under his bed, and write the great King at three or foure words into trembling: That can ſend <note place="margin">Adrian the fourth Acts and Monum.</note> a Fly to fetch the Triple Crown before his Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and make a hair, or the kernel of a Raiſin, as mortall as <hi>Goliah</hi> his ſpear: That can unſpeake the whole world into nothing, and blowe down a great bubble with an eaſie breath: That by drawing one nail, can throw down the ſtatelieſt building, and undreſſe your ſouls by unpinning one pin. If he take the Bridle off the head of that fire that's in you, it preſently burns you up, by a Fever. If he looſe the water, it drownes you, by a Dropſie. If he lay his hand upon your mouth, he takes away the airy difference betweene ſleep and death. He ſaith to <hi>Moſes, Go up and die:</hi> and it follows after, <hi>Moſes my ſervant is dead.</hi> Every man hath a day which is called <hi>His day:</hi> and death never makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, <note place="margin">1 Sam. 28. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Non eſt inventus in baliva noſtra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſubject of this Lamentation is a Prince and a great man fallen in the time of his agency &amp; uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for the ſettlement of the deſtractions of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The key of the ſtory unlocks the ſenſe of theſe words <hi>This day in Iſrael.</hi> It was a time that the promiſe of God to <hi>David</hi> was at the birth, and the Midwivery of <hi>Abner</hi> was offered. Let <hi>Abner</hi> otherwiſe be what he will for a man; <hi>God may uſe an Egyptian midwife to bring forth the child of an Iſraelite.</hi> But this great man
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:29677:10"/> falls in the very nicke of time, before the good iſſue of his deſignes. Let me point out this Obſervation to you:</p>
               <p>Its not unuſuall, that <hi>great builders catch a fall when they are upon the ſcaffold aboute their worke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Oh how it amazeth the faith of Gods people, when the ſtar that led them out of their own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, goes out of ſight before it have brought them to their journeys end. That youngling world of Reformation in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, had a ſore temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, when it muſt ſee the fall (as I may ſay) of the Electour of <hi>Saxony</hi> and others that were pillars of hope. <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt live no longer then to bring <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the plains of <hi>Moab:</hi> himſelfe is allowed but a proſpect of that he hoped to have enjoyed, and to have brought <hi>Iſrael</hi> into We are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preſidents: our eyes have ſeen ſome of our grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter lights eclipſed, <hi>pleno orbe,</hi> when they have been at their Full. The great God that hides his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, knows his Works from the begining to the end, and he takes off ſuch Inſtruments that he may ſhew that he doth not <hi>need,</hi> is not <hi>tied</hi> to any tool: for he made the great world without any. When he ſaith <hi>Faciamus,</hi> he ſpeaks to himſelfe alone; not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and man. Thus he makes way for ſome other Providence to come upon the Stage, and brings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his Worke by a more crooked Inſtrument, which wee imagined ſhould be done by a ſtrait one. So <hi>Iſrael</hi> is ſpeedily reduced to <hi>David,</hi> though <hi>Abner</hi> fall. Or he humbles his people juſt before his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes take effect; and firſt ſtrikes them dumb before he open their mouthes in a <hi>Benedicite;</hi> that the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of his handmaidens may break forth into a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29677:11"/> 
                  <hi>Magnificat:</hi> or the time is not yet come that <hi>Iſrael</hi> is to be brought out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> and therefore though <hi>Moſes</hi> begin to reſcue the <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> and ſlay the <hi>Egyptian,</hi> yet he muſt flee for it, and be hidden for Fourty years. Or elſe he pulls the ſtool of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence from under us, becauſe we ſit down upon it: or elſe pulls up the ſluce of ſome judgements which have been hindr'd by ſome <hi>Lot</hi> or great man, or whatſoever it be. We ſee that God writes the Names of our beſt and greateſt men in the ſhell, and takes them away by a kind of Oſtraciſme. All the help, hope, and comfort is, that God hath all inſtruments eminently in himſelfe, and can raiſe up a <hi>Ioſhua</hi> in ſteed of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Wherefore if his Diſciples cannot caſt out the evill Spirit, let us come to himſelfe, and make our ſelves as ſure of his Word by faith, as he is ſure of his word by promiſe; for though <hi>Ioſeph</hi> die in Egypt, yet he layes his bones at ſtake, that God will ſurely viſit his Iſrael, <hi>Gen. vlt. ver.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p n="5">5. All this that hath been ſaid, a Prince, a great man fallen at ſuch a time, <hi>is juſt reaſon of ſad and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne lamentation;</hi> and therefore <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> is in this mourning poſture: ſuch a man whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence had a large circumference or ſphaere while he lived, is followed by an honour and ſorrow of the ſame compaſſe when he dyes: You <hi>Princes and great men,</hi> death will tell what the world thought of you; while you live (it may be) Sycophants &amp; flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers lay their egges in your eares, and hatch mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous opinions in you of your greatneſſe. Such Rooks uſually build in the higheſt Trees; and on the other ſide, envy &amp; detraction may breath upon the glaſſe of your reputation, that it ſhall not (while you
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:29677:11"/> live) report ſo cleare an Image of you, but death wil make thorow-lights in you; that you ſhall be ſeen on both ſides; ſorrows will not, cannot be tongue-tyed; you will then begin to reape your due. Then the world breaks out into theſe expreſſions; Hee was a brave man, He was a great Courtier, that could not be curbed with a white ſtaffe, to bee of counſell to ſubvert the freedomes of his Countrey; He was a Captain that could draw a line, but not to the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble center of his private ends; He was a Juſtice that would ſcatter the drunkards from their Ale-bench, and did not underſtand the language of a bottle or a basket; He was a <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> whoſe kindneſſes were great which he ſhewed to the houſe of God, and the Offices thereof; He was a Miniſter that could not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thunder in his Doctrine, but lighten in his Life; He was a <hi>Papinian</hi> (a great Lawyer) but hee would not defend Imperiall and arbitrary exorbitances, though he dyed for it; He was a man that appeared &amp; ſtood for the truth, and for God in the worſt times, when the <hi>Summer birds</hi> were hidden in their hollow Trees; He was a man firm and fixed, and ſtudied not the neutral art of putting off the cap to one, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a leg to another. And is not this a brave Eccho, are not ſuch men worthy of the Honourable tears of Iſrael? or elſe Iſrael hath reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to mourn for the ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe and ſtupidity of their own hearts. And for the State and honour of mourning, it is an ancient ſolemnity credited by time, and great examples, yea, and almoſt the common ſenſe of mankind. For both Egyptians and Iſraelites concurre in weeping for <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> whoſe Exequies were performed in great Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page when he was cared out of Egypt; and not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29677:12"/> in more examples, its ſaid of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> that all Judah and inhabitants of Jeruſalem, did him ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note place="margin">2 Chron. 32, 33.</note> at his death, and laid him up in the higheſt Cell of the Sepulchers of <hi>Davids</hi> ſons, ſuch is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victive Majeſty of goodneſs, that this idolatrous-hearted people follow their great Reformer to his grave with honour. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De purgat. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>In vaine doth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> goe about to prove out of theſe ſolemnities, that they are done <hi>ad juvandas animas.</hi> Wee find no Law of ſacrifices for the dead, theſe expreſſions are but civill <hi>indexes</hi> of honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſorrowes, a debt owing to Worthies while they liv'd, and the remainder paid at their death: Like the after-beames of the Sun, which follow him to his bed; and we were unworthy heires of their famous acts, if out of their owne goods we could not allow them anſwerable interrment; and if any Cynicke in his moroſity ſhall ſay, that it matters not, <hi>humine an in ſublimi putreſcat,</hi> Let him enjoy a Philoſophicall rotting in what ditch he pleaſe; we know, there is the buriall of an Aſſe; the graves of the common people, which is ſomething above that <note place="margin">2 Chron. 21. 20.</note> and higher yet, there is a buriall in the City of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> but not in the Sepulchers of the Kings, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Sepulchers of the Kings, There are low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and higher Cells. Honour will follow after worth and merit even into its grave. We doe not lay up the carkaſſe of every Cole-ſhip with that reſpect as that of <hi>Drakes</hi> was; though confeſſedly the one muſt rot, as well as the other.</p>
               <p>So much for the opening of the point; Now I come to the words, <hi>Doe you not know,</hi> by their hand to ſerve in the uſes of this point.</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29677:13"/>
                  <item>1. <hi>Know ye not,</hi> You Princes and great men that ye muſt fall.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Know ye not,</hi> You lower Shrubs, that theſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars muſt fall.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For you that are Princes and great men, I may ſay of you as <hi>X<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rxes</hi> weeping, ſaid of his vaſt Army, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few luſters of yeares, there ſhall not be one of you ſtanding, but all fallen, and let me ſet this deaths-head before you: For I have no other diſh, nor am I likely ever to entertaine ſuch a Table-full of ſo great gueſts while I live againe; let it therefore,</p>
               <p>Firſt, Humble you, and give me leave to follow the chariot of your greatneſſe, with <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that you muſt fall. Greatneſſe hath need of ſome correctives. You are ſuch Pictures, that if one ſtand of the one ſide of you, <hi>You are Gods;</hi> but if he looke upon you on the other ſide, <hi>You are men,</hi> and muſt dye <hi>like men:</hi> this takes you one ſtep lower; nay, we may goe lower yet; For man being in honour without underſtanding, is <hi>like the beaſts</hi> that periſh. We are all proud; pride is the ſhirt of the ſoule, which it puts off laſt when it ſhifts: And every riſing ground of authority or power, makes us riſe in thoughts. The very bramble, if it get a ſnatch of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, will be talking of his ſhadow. Oh that you had the meeknes of that <hi>Moſes,</hi> whoſe face did ſhine, but he knew not that (I ſpeake this by alluſion) the skin of his face did ſhine. I would that but every tenth thought of your riſing, was accompanied with one thought of your falling: And yet you have more reaſon to have death in your eyes then other men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Venice Glaſſes, and China mettall of your fine and tender bodies, will not abide ſo great a ſtroak as other earthen pots of courſer mettall; I will not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29677:14"/> offer to you thoſe complements with death, whereof we read good ſtore, in uſe among great men; as the boy that cry'd, <hi>Memento te mortalem;</hi> or that, of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting ſeverall ſorts of Marble to the Emperor upon his Coronation day, that he might then chuſe which he would have for his Tombe, &amp;c. But let me preſſe the ſenſe of your falling condition to humble you. I doe not meane by humilitie a morall familiarity or courteſie toward thoſe of lower ranke, which yet is agracefull condeſcency of Greatneſſe: But I meane, a ſtooping to the reproofes of the Word of God, brought unto you by the Miniſters thereof, who are but earthen veſſels like your ſelves: Submit your cheek to reproofs, for your owne fins, and of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. Let not your iniquities take ſanctuary in your greatneſſe; Frowne not your Chaplaines into a meal-mouth'd baſeneſſe, ſo that they dare no more make a darke or oblique reflection upon your darling ſins, then take a Beare by the tooth. If you will bleed out your ill bloud, you muſt pull off your Velvet ſleeve, and let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>me be bare to the point of the knife: Keep no State againſt God, though he ſpeake thunder and lightning by the mouth of duſt like your ſelves. A man never makes worſe uſe of his greatneſſe, then by it to caſt a muzzle over the mouth of ſound and ſearching reproofes. And it is a juſt judgment of God upon ſuch men, that they ſhould have Prophets, that will ſay to <hi>Ahab, Goe up and proſper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, Quicken you to activity in your places while you live, that you may ſerve your generation according to the will of God before you dye, and ſee corruption; otherwiſe, you are but blind lights in gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſticks: You are in great debt, both to the Church and Common-wealth, they have truſted you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:29677:14"/> with all they have, and your bond is good; but yet be not offended, if they call hard upon you to pay your debts, for you are mortall men, and we know not what Heires or Executors you may leave behind you. The Creditor is oftentimes broken in the Debtors death; Get death into your minds, and it will put life into your actions; what you found made of poore Bricke, leave in ſtately Marble, and be not like many, who while they are riſing, appeare very active and ſtirring men; but when they are up, doe freeze into a benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſlowneſſe, like Bels that ſtrike thicke when they are riſing, and afterwards when they are at full pitch, are ſet; put your ſelves on with this ſpurre, I muſt ſhortly dye: How ſhould I live fruitfully? The night will come, how ſhould I labour while it is day? I wiſh well to things that are good: but <hi>(Bene <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogitare eſt bene ſomniare)</hi> a good thinker is but a good dreamer; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſads and duls the heart when one comes to dye, than his neglect of ſuch opportunities which Gods providence, or his owne place have p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t into his hand of receiving &amp; doing good. Not is there a ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per corroſive, than the reflection upon thoſe dayes and times that have paſſed over him, <hi>Male, aliud, nihil, agentem.</hi> The higheſt hils are the barrenneſt ground, and I would that ſaying did not ſo truly ſquare to great Ones (that is) that the goodlieſt Trees, as Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, &amp;c. doe either beare none, or the worſt Fruit. Great parts and abilities without exerciſe and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth are but ſecret and unknowne Mines of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and Gold, which lye hid in an unfruitfull and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſoyle. And therfore, you the great and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Worthies, in whoſe hands are the Publike Faith, the Publike Mercy, the Publike Juſtice, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Peace; be good, and (let your goodnes make you)
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:29677:15"/> quicke diſpenſers of what you have in Stewardſhip, becauſe the time is ſhort, and the word <hi>redde rationem</hi> may be given ſuddenly, look upon us as mortall men, who ſhall not live long to receive, and upon your ſelves, who ſhall not live long to give the fruits of your hands. And becauſe the Occaſion invites me, let me propound an object to your charitable juſtice, that is, the relief of thoſe great ſufferers who have bin great doers, I meane the firſt adventurers with this great Commander, when he firſt cut through the Alps. As for the great and doubtfull matters that are under your hand, I would not be thought ſo raſh, as to wiſh you to precipitate: A Pilot among ſhelves and rocks may be too quick; A <hi>Cunctator</hi> ſometime ſaved the Common-wealth; only thus I may pray, that when the Haven lyes faire before you, and is without barre, you may <hi>fortiter occupare,</hi> ſet in ſtifly, leſt new waves, raiſed by croſſe winds, carry you backe into the Main againe.</p>
               <p>3. Arme you againſt your fall that the day therof may be to you (as the Paſſion-day of the Martyrs was called) the birth-day of Eternity. <hi>Nequaquam morte mortemini,</hi> was the inlet of our ſin and miſery, &amp; keeps the doore open to ſin ſtill; The Epicure hath his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt death: a ſenſeleſſe conſideration of it, as of a nothing, or a not being. The great Spirit hath his Armour too; A contempt of death out of principles of Valour and Honour; but neither of theſe Armours can keep the arrow from the quicke; There is a terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble clauſe in the Statute of dying, <hi>And after that the judgement.</hi> Nor yet will I goe about to arme you with this meditation, that we ſhall have a ſhorter journey from death to life again, than we had from not being, unto life, or that which is cited by <hi>Gerard</hi> out of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29677:15"/> that all the time that hath run, or ſhall run out from the beginning, to the end, ſhall ſeeme to <hi>Adam</hi> when he riſeth againe, but <hi>tanquam ſomnus unius horae,</hi> as the ſleep of the body for one houre; But if you will breake the fall, which elſe will breake you, then you <hi>Gods</hi> muſt become <hi>Saints</hi> (for all Gods are not Saints) the death of Saints is more precious then the death of Gods; Grace is ſpeciall baile againſt death, there is no gall and vinegar in it to be drunk by them, for whom Chriſt hath already drunke it: <hi>Death</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) <hi>is yours,</hi> becauſe contributory and ſubſervient to your happines; That life which is hid with Chriſt in God, is out of the reach of death, our Saviour proves <hi>Abraham</hi> to be living, becauſe God had long after his death, ſaid, I am the God of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Thoſe that are confederate with God in Covenant, muſt always live, that the Covenant may not be diſſolved by the death of the one party. There is a way then to break the teeth of death, and to be immortall: Have God for your God; labour to have ſomething in you that is immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall beſides your very ſouls; lay up for your ſelves a treaſure beyond the ſea of death, that when this <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brana dignitatis</hi> (as <hi>Seneca</hi> cals it) a thin skin of honour breaks, you may not be quite bankrupts; enrich your ſouls with the power of godlines, which is profitable to all things. The place of Princes, the magnificence and great works of great men; The faith and godlines of poore men doe make a rare compoſition. Do not in ſtead of diſarming death, arme it rather againſt you, by putting a ſword into the hand of it. The more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that you may doe by the advantage of ground you ſtand upon, the heavyer will your accounts be, if your greatnes be made a Stage and Theater for to act the parts of luxury, laſciviouſnes, oppreſſion upon. What
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29677:16"/> difference is there between ſuch gods, and thoſe in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> of whoſe drunkenneſſe and adulteries there is frequent mention; let me ſpeake one word to you, young Noblemen, and Gentlemen, Learne you the way of godlineſſe, that may free you from the looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vanitie incident to greatneſſe; for when you have given <hi>florem Diabolo,</hi> the floure of your time to luſts of youth; your fall may come before you can ſo much as give <hi>faecem Deo,</hi> the dregs thereof to God.</p>
               <p>I conclude this point with that which one obſerves upon Gods ſeeing all the works that he had made, that they were <hi>very good,</hi> for then immediately (ſaith he) followed the Sabbath, or reſt of God, which (though our ſalvation be not of workes) may ſignifie thus much to you, that when you ſhall come to a retroſpect upon your wayes and works, and find them ſo empty of, and contrary unto God, there can be no expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Sabbath or reſt unto your ſoules; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>waſh ye, make ye cleane, &amp;c.</hi> Iſa. 1. 16, 17.</p>
               <p>The ſecond, <hi>Know ye not,</hi> is ſpoken to you, the lower ſhrubs. You are to know that your great men may fall in the very time of their uſefulneſſe and ſervice for your good. In their loſſe, bewaile your ſins: for though you feele not the ſtroke while the wound is freſh and green, yet afterwards you will find the want of ſuch as are worthy inſtruments, when wee expect they ſhould doe great things; God by taking them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, interrupts the caſt. Put not therefore your truſt in Princes, nor in the ſon of man, in whom there is no ſalvation; for his breath goeth forth, and in that very day his thoughts periſh, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 146. 3, 4. even his projects and intentions for your good, dye in the wombe, and are abortive. If we leane hard upon the reed, it breaks the ſooner, and wee are laid flat on the ground.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:29677:16"/> God will not let his people enjoy that long, which they prize too much, ſome worme ſhall ſmite that gourd, and it ſhall wither; and though many great men are not likely to be blaſted by the confidence of the people, yet our ſad experience teacheth us, that we ſmell too much to our ſweeteſt flowers, and ſo wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them.</p>
               <p>I Shall now come to the paralell Herſe of that <hi>Prince and great man</hi> fallen this day in <hi>England,</hi> of whom, though modeſtie it ſelfe may without bluſhing ſpeak in a magnificent ſtile, yet have my thoughts waved me too and fro, it not being eaſie to be moderatour of the Arguments that are for ſpeech, or ſilence: Not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the matter will ſurpaſſe the work-manſhip, and the copiouſneſſe of the ſubject ſhame, the penury of my expreſſion; but becauſe on the one hand it is argued, that Funerall Encomiaſtickes of the dead, are very often confections of poyſon to the living; for many, whoſe lives ſpeake nothing for them, will draw the example into conſequence, and be thereby led in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hope, that they may preſſe a hackny Funerall Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to carry them to Heaven when they dye; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, if ſuch for whom no file could be rough enough while they lived, be ſmooth-filed when they are dead: on the other hand it may be ſaid, That though co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon graves have no inſcription, yet Marble Tombes are not without ſome Epitaph. Heroicall examples ſhould not go with a common paſſe, but with a Trom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet. <hi>David</hi> afforded this Honorary to <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Abner,</hi> and (which is to be obſerved) he drew not any line in their pictures with a black coale, which yet he might have done, for both of them had too much ſhadow if he would have uſed it; but he dealt with them as the Painter did with <hi>Antigonus,</hi> who had but one eye, he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:29677:17"/> drew his Picture, <hi>imagine luſca</hi> halfe-faced, and ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the deformitie out of the beholders ſight.</p>
               <p>Neither is this all, which makes me ſtand in a ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery place, but the various ſenſes and cenſures too, which are very likely to be found in this great multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: Some that hated the ſound of his Drums and Trumpets, will not patiently endure the Ecchore-ſounding to their diſ-affected eares. And ſome againe are indifferently content to heare ſome good words of his Epitaph, becauſe it begins with <hi>Hîc jacet,</hi> here he lyes; as <hi>Caracalla</hi> ſaid to them that deſired, that ſome honours might be ſpent upon his Brother <hi>Geta,</hi> now dead out of his way: <hi>Sit divus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>modo non ſit vivus,</hi> honour him as you will, ſo as he doth not live. The moſt voyces will doubtleſſe vote, that it is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to ſet up a Candle to the Sunne, for his ſtory is yet alive in all mens memories, and the ſtage where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he acted it, is yet warme. The truth is, I had rather leave him to the hiſtory, which I hope the honourable Houſes have beſpoken, and to that <hi>Homer</hi> that ſhall be the <hi>praco</hi> of this <hi>Achilles.</hi> But becauſe his name would ſometime have paſſed me clear through all Guards, and probably hath not as yet loſt that vertue; and that this State and preſence ſpeakes him with more eloquence, then I, ſo that I can but run the hazard of being an imperfect interpreter by word, of that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which your ſelves doe ſpeake by ſignes. And ſince death hath put him beyond pride, all beyond en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and my ſelfe beyond flattery, what if wee make a ſhort Index of his Story, and audit his <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bentur</hi> in the mean time, not drawing him in full proportion, but as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> pourtrayed the Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> upon a Tile, which wil indeed be more ſuitable to the poſture we are in; for deepe ſorrowes make no long orations, <hi>Leves loquuntur curae, ingentes ſtupent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:29677:18"/>
               <p> Since then it muſt be ſo, <hi>jacta eſt alea;</hi> I ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon my ſelf this law, not to build his Monument of common ſtones, nor trouble my ſelf and you, to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch flowers to caſt upon his grave, as grow in common fields, nor deſcend or ſtoope to any thing which is beneath <hi>Heroicall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Nobilitie</hi> and his <hi>Nobleneſſe,</hi> though they might each of them adorne his Monument, yet the third, which is his <hi>Excellency,</hi> is the tranſcendent.</p>
               <p>For <hi>his Nobilitie;</hi> He was ſprung of an exceeding faire, an ancient Stem, which doth branch forth into the great and Noble Families of the Princes and great men of <hi>England,</hi> and he was the third of this Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which was inoculate into that Stem, by Q. <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> of famous memory, <hi>But Titles of Honour muſt dye as well as men;</hi> and becauſe this renowned ſtreame carries it's name no further, I ſhall omit all matter of Heraldry, as not becomming me at this time and place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Nobleneſſe</hi> was of a high and honourable eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; He was a man of fixed principles, and of a maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine reſolution, of an inviting familiarity in a ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preſence; too generous to be cruell, too great a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot to be Courted; his compaſſe without trepida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or variation, had conſtantly ſtood right to that Pole; the good of his Country, which he kept in his eye, both when he wore the Gowne, and Sword: He was <hi>fidè Romana &amp; Anti-Romana,</hi> of Roman faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of Anti-Roman faith: A Senatour that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured his Robes. The teares of <hi>England,</hi> of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, of his tenants, do ſpeake him in a better langu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age then the moſt eloquent Marble is able: Though tenants teares be no commendation to a living land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, yet are they credit to the dead.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29677:19"/>
               <p> The Character of his <hi>Excellency,</hi> may be that which <hi>David</hi> ſometime gave to <hi>Abner,</hi> the great man in my Text; <hi>Art not thou a valiant man, and who is like thee in all Iſrael?</hi> When the time was come that <hi>Ianus</hi> Temple muſt be open'd here in England, by the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that onely hath the key of it, Neceſſitie, and thoſe orphane ſiſters (before ſpoken of) Libertie and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie were to chuſe their Guardian, Champion and <hi>Vindex;</hi> you the Honourable Truſtees, looked out for a <hi>Dictator,</hi> in whoſe hands you might depoſite, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being, ſafety, freedom, lives, <hi>Senatus populique Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> of the Parliament and people of England, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily pitcht your eye and choyce upon this man, who was <hi>ſtirpe &amp; ingenio bellicoſus,</hi> One that had honour to give credit to the Cauſe he undertooke, reputation to vindicate his undertaking from contempt of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; Intereſt, whoſe Drum could preſſe an Army; dexteritie to manage the Sword, Counſell to direct it, Valour to uſe it, &amp; faithfulneſſe to diſcharge it. And he was the man you then reſolv'd to <hi>live</hi> and <hi>dye</hi> with. It was the greateſt honour in the world, to be credited with the infinite <hi>depoſitum</hi> of the life and being of the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> And at this time, when you had aſſigned this Theater to act his part upon, it was the higheſt honour to him, that he would undertake to Pilot a Ship ſo laden with ſo great a fraught, through the tempeſtuous and angry Seas which then began to ſwell and be intractable, when this poore Kingdome, knew not for the moſt part, how to weare Buffe and Steele, untill taught by him; in whom that ancient Chivalry and Valour of <hi>England</hi> (which had left it's Monuments in <hi>France</hi> and other parts of the world, but of later times almoſt emaſculate and grown obſolet) was concenter'd, and by tranſmigration had layd
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:29677:19"/> it ſelfe up in him: He was the man that was to breake the yce, and ſet his firſt footing in the Red Sea; a <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules,</hi> but not <hi>in bivio;</hi> a man reſolved, when others hung in ſuſpence; fixt, when ſome ſtarres of greateſt magnitude were moved with trepidation, or erratick. That filled the breach, when many lay <hi>poſt principa,</hi> &amp; behind the hedge. No Proclamation of Treaſon could cry him down, nor threatning Standard daunt him: That in that miſty morning, when men knew not each the other, whether friend or foe, by his ariſing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel'd the fogge, and by his very name, commanded thouſands into your ſervice. Such as were for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and groaned under preſſures in Religion, he tooke by the hand, and they him: Such as were Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots, and would ſtand up for common Liberties, he tooke by the hand, and they him, and ſo became the bond or knot of both, as the Axletree of the world upon which both the Poles doe move: And this muſt be his honour alone for ever; for though <hi>Ioſhua</hi> alſo doe admirably when he comes to it, yet it is <hi>Moſes</hi> that firſt leads forth Iſrael by their Armies.</p>
               <p>Thus he enter'd, and for his deportment upon the Stage, and the experience he gave of himſelfe, who knowes not it? Such was his <hi>perſonall valour,</hi> as if no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſteele had gone to his compoſition. The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances are famous; In that great battell at Edge-hill, where this Kingdome had her firſt <hi>Criſis</hi> upon a Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day, (our wars have now fulfilled above halfe a weeke of yeares) when he had loſt a wing yet he flew a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, <hi>Et nullo diſcrimine, notum, dux an miles erat;</hi> He ſhewed his Army there what a man they had adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured with, in their firſt Voyage; No, I <hi>prae ſequar,</hi> Captaine, but one whoſe Valour gave the word <hi>ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini me,</hi> with whoſe ſteele (its no diſparagement to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:29677:20"/> ſay, that) his for ever famous Chieftaines ſharpned their edge, and ſo that hill was made a ſtanding Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phee, your enemies (Right Honourable) from that day begun to take you for a Parliament.</p>
               <p>I muſt leave to the large Map of his Story, thoſe many memorables &amp; victories, which bear his name; for even great places doe not always find any room in a little Map, and ſhall inſtance him but in one other particular, that famous expedition to <hi>Glouceſter,</hi> when we were at a very low water, and this Eagle had then alſo moulted his feathers, and having imped them with renowned Londoners, did fight the greateſt part of that long march thither, where the then Governour whom I may (borrowing <hi>Cicero</hi> his word) call <hi>hujus Regni Stator,</hi> the Stator of the Kingdome of England, (becauſe he tooke the enemy his horſe by the bridle in his full career, and ſtopt him, and being reſolved to ſell that City to them by the candle) was reſcued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the candle dropt, by this noble Champion, who retreating from that Tropick, fought his way backe againe through hunger and hardſhip: and becauſe this Retreat ſhould not be like an empty field without ſome charge, He ſcattered that great Army near <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery,</hi> and to you this renowned City, <hi>reddidit Legiones,</hi> reſtored your valiant Legions, and reſtored England to it ſelfe; An unparalell'd Expedition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Faithfulnes</hi> was like Touch or Marble without any ſtreaming flaw, no Honours, Offices, or whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever beares the name of greatneſſe could bribe it. The two Indies would have bin as dirt: He knew the Pole he muſt ſaile by, and ſteered not by a mercenary Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. He had eſpouſed the Senate and Liberties of England, and was reſolved, <hi>aut liberare fidem, aut ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere animam.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29677:20"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>His ends,</hi> ſo far as one may learne the marke by the Archers eye, were not private intereſts, reſpects, or parties, to be ſerved upon the aſhes of publike ruins. Talk of gold to ſouldiers of fortune, He was <hi>Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocles.</hi> A right line drawne from the Center you ſet him, would have cut the center of his aimes and ends. Had you falne upon ſuch a Merchant as would have been eccentricke to you, and have cauponated the war to raiſe his private intereſt, or have put in the great fraught he was truſted with, and conſigned the Carga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zone, to ſome Royall Port, oh, what a Ferall Table of Proſcriptions, (like that of <hi>Syllae's)</hi> might have bin ſet up amongſt us; and your lives have bin bargain'd for, and ſold as that Triumvirate did the lives of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours of Rome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His Counſell</hi> and wiſedome was ſuch as argued him to be a man that knew conduct; He had a fine finger to find out, and skilfull to untie or cut the knot, In fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of danger his eyes were open; but when he came to execute his Councels, his eyes were ſhut againſt all impreſſions of feare and terrour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>His love and reſpect</hi> to the Souldiery, ſuch as became a brave Chriſtian. He would not Turkiſhly fill ditch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or ſtop Canon with them. His hand of reliefe was not ſhut or ſhort to reſcued priſoners. He affourded honourable reſpect to naked and wounded valour. His countenance paid and arm'd his ſouldiers, when ſometimes they wanted both: and no wonder if his Schoole bred ſuch a gallant Infantry which had ſuch a Maſter, and ſuch an Uſher.</p>
               <p>In ſumme. This <hi>Camillus</hi> was a ſecond <hi>Romulus.</hi> His Monument needs no inſcription, for his Epitaph is written in the hearts of men. Nothing but <hi>ESSEX,</hi> the Great, the Valiant, the Faithfull, the Parliaments
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:29677:21"/> 
                  <hi>Eſſex;</hi> the <hi>Eſſex</hi> of England, and the <hi>Tutelar</hi> thereof: who added to his Noble Coronet all the Militarie Crownes, ſaving that which is called Navall, or the Sea-Crowne, which is due to another moſt Noble Worthy, more faithfull than the Element he was then the Maſter of.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>For his death,</hi> the Forlorne hope it ſent out before it, was but ſleightly, the Phyſicians thought him bailable, but death lay in ambuſcado in a full body, &amp; ſuddenly ſurprized him with a dying ſleep, and now we are erecting of his Monument, one of the ſeven wonders of the World was a Tombe. And if the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Famous men who fought under his Banner, ſhall pleaſe to be ſet in for his ſupporters, it will be ſuch a Squadron-Monument as will have no Brother in England, untill the time doe come (and I wiſh it may be long firſt) that the moſt renowned and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Champion that now governes the ſword of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, muſt now lay his bones by him, and then there will be the <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega</hi> of ſuch a Story as ſhall render God <hi>fearfull in prayſes, doing wonders</hi> by the firſt hand of him that led us through the untrodden paths of the wilderneſſe, and by the ſecond hand of him that hath made Victory (which <hi>Homer</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Jack on both ſides) to change its name; who if he ſhall have but one ſtone out of each City or ſtrong Hold taken by his Armes, to make his Tombe, it will be ſuch a Monument that every ſtone of it will ſpeak a Hiſtory, and ſome a Miracle: Or if that cannot be, it will be enough that he lay his head upon an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall Turff taken out of Naſeby field: God thought <hi>Moſes,</hi> or rather made him the fitteſt man to begin, &amp; lead Iſrael forth, and he honored <hi>Ioſhua</hi> with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating of the worke, neither doth <hi>Ioſhua</hi> eclipſe the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29677:21"/> worth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> nor he the worth of <hi>Ioſhua;</hi> and ſo cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pardon of my boldneſſe with your patience, I have endeavoured to ſpeak wthout reflections upon any, nor did I mean to tread on the foot or toe of any man, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to raiſe my ſpeech the higher, as knowing that this Prince and great man needed not to pull downe the ſtones of any other mans Monument to build his, who had enow in his owne Quarry, as being (nex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Parliament) <hi>that firſt man</hi> from whom we paſſe to our poſterity the conveyancies of our liberty and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. <hi>Et nati natorum, &amp; qui naſcentur ab illis.</hi> I have no more but this; He lived <hi>a good Generall,</hi> He dyed <hi>a Generall good;</hi> and therefore a lamentation to all Iſrael, and ſo I leave him in his Bed of Honour, and draw the Curtains, and put out the lights.</p>
               <p>Only a word at parting, and firſt <hi>my Lords</hi> to you, we may know how great the Tree that's fallen, was, by the vacuity or void place it leaves behind it. We look upon you as them that will endeavour to prevent the <hi>vacuum</hi> by acting from that noble principle which moves to the univerſall and common good; the loſſe we have ſuſtained is great, though he never had wore Buff but only Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Robes, and they ſay that when a limbe or part of a man is cut off, <hi>anima retrahitur,</hi> the ſoule is retracted. I wiſh the Philoſophy may be verefied in the retraction of his reality and faithfulneſſe unto you; that ſo he may remaine among you in quinteſſence and vertue, being as it were divided among you, as they ſay of <hi>Romulus,</hi> that he was diſcerpt by the Senate, when he dyed, and every Senatour got a piece of him. Let nothing that was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary in him be put in his grave, that neither we nor our poſterity may have cauſe to write upon his Statue, as they did upon that of <hi>Brutus, utinam viveres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for his Military worth; If any ſhall apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:29677:22"/> to copy it out, or ſome young Noble Spark ſhall pleaſe to goe to Schoole to his Monument, their leſſon is, <hi>Diſce Miles militare, Galba eſt.</hi> Here they ſhal be taught how to excell, <hi>fide &amp; armis,</hi> How to have mettell in their Coat, as well as Colour; How to carry themſelves ſo, as they may <hi>legere exercitum, non emere,</hi> win an Army and not preſſe, ſilence mutinies, or perſwade the ſouldiery with one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord <hi>Quirites,</hi> and in a word how to be an <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex,</hi> not a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who converted his Arms againſt the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and therefore hath a blot in his Copy to this day.</p>
               <p>I muſt conclude with you the moſt Honourable Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of England; It would be too much preſumption in me to thanke you for this Honour of your preſence and ſorrowes; Its a great thing to be made immortall by an immortall Parliament: All the Honour which belongs to your ſervants and inſtruments, redounds to you; what they get or receive is but handed by them to you the owners; ſhould we write downe but fifty to them, when there is a hundred due, the loſſe would be yours. It was a ſtately deportment to entertaine the newe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this great Champion and Senatour his death, as the old Romans uſed to entertaine ſad tydings, <hi>mutatis veſtibus,</hi> and to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour your ſorrow with an adjournment: This is the way to breed more <hi>Eſſex's:</hi> Its Honour that breeds a ſouldier; Take honour out of his eye, and you cut off the ſpurres from his heeles. My wiſhes are, firſt, that you may never have occaſion to create any moe then you have done by the name of Excellency: ſecondly, that if you muſt, there may be ſuch men, with whom in ſafety you may lay up your lives, and thirdly, that you may have the happines to pitch upon them. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>P.</hi> 15. <hi>l. ult. for</hi> cared, r. carried <hi>p.</hi> 26. <hi>l.</hi> 24 <hi>r.</hi> aſſigned him <hi>p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 23 <hi>for</hi> Chriſtian, <hi>r.</hi> Chreſtaine <hi>p.</hi> 30. <hi>l.</hi> 19. <hi>put out</hi> now. <hi>p</hi> 32, <hi>l.</hi> 8. <hi>for</hi> accord, <hi>r.</hi> word.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
